Part 4 You will hear an anthropology student giving
a presentation on spiral path designs known as labyrinth.
First you have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
you
Now listen carefully and answer questions 31 to 40.
Labyrinths have existed for well over 4,000 years.
Labyrinths and labyrinthine symbols have been found in regions as diverse as modern-day
Turkey, Ireland, Greece and India.
There are various designs of labyrinth but what they all have in common is a winding
spiral path which leads to a central area.
There is one starting point at the entrance and the goal is to reach the central area.
Finding your way through a labyrinth involves many twists and turns but it's not possible
to get lost as there is only one single path.
In modern times the word labyrinth has taken on a different meaning and is often used as
a synonym for a maze.
A maze is quite different as it is a kind of puzzle with an intricate network of paths.
Mases became fashionable in the 15th and 16th centuries in Europe and can still be found
in the gardens of great houses and palaces.
The paths are usually surrounded by thick high hedges so that it's not possible to
see over them.
Entering a maze usually involves getting lost a few times before using logic to work out
the pattern and find your way to the centre and then out again.
There are lots of dead ends and paths which lead you back to where you started.
The word maze is believed to come from a Scandinavian word for a state of confusion.
This is where the word amazing comes from.
Labyrinths on the other hand have a very different function.
Although people now often refer to things they find complicated as labyrinths, this
is not how they were seen in the past.
The winding spiral of the labyrinth has been used for centuries as a metaphor for life's
journey.
It served as a spiritual reminder that there is purpose and meaning to our lives and helped
to give people a sense of direction.
Labyrinths are thought to encourage a feeling of calm and have been used as a meditation
and prayer tool in many cultures over many centuries.
The earliest examples of the labyrinth spiral pattern have been found carved into stone
from Sardinia to Scandinavia, from Arizona to India to Africa.
In Europe these spiral carvings date from the late Bronze Age.
The Native American Pima tribe wove baskets with a circular labyrinth design that depicted
their own cosmology.
In ancient Greece the labyrinth spiral was used on coins around 4000 years ago.
Labyrinths made of mosaics were commonly found in bathhouses, villas and tombs throughout
the Roman Empire.
In Northern Europe there were actual physical labyrinths designed for walking on.
These were cut into the turf or grass, usually in a circular pattern.
The origin of these walking labyrinths remains unclear but they were probably used for fertility
rites which may date back thousands of years.
Eleven examples of turf labyrinths survive today, including the largest one at Saffron
Walden, England, which used to have a large tree in the middle of it.
More recently labyrinths have experienced something of a revival.
Some believe that walking a labyrinth promotes healing and mindfulness and there are those
who believe in its emotional and physical benefits which include slower breathing and
a restored sense of balance and perspective.
This idea has become so popular that labyrinths have been laid into the floors of spars, wellness
centres and even prisons in recent years.
A pamphlet at Colorado Children's Hospital informs patients that walking a labyrinth can
often calm people in the midst of a crisis.
And apparently it's not only patients who benefit.
Many visitors find walking a labyrinth less stressful than sitting in a corridor or waiting
room.
Some doctors even walk the labyrinth during their breaks.
In some hospitals patients who can't walk can have a paper finger labyrinth brought
to their bed.
The science behind the theory is a little sketchy but there are dozens of small scale
studies which support claims about the benefits of labyrinths.
For example, one study found that walking a labyrinth provided short term calming, relaxation
and relief from anxiety for Alzheimer's patients.
So what is it about labyrinths that makes their appeal so universal?
That is the end of part four.
You now have one minute to check your answers to part four.
That is the end of the listening test.
In the IELTS test, you would now have ten minutes to transfer your answers to the answer
sheet.